"Resveratrol Tested for Alzheimer’s, Arthritis, and Osteoporosis"
Does resveratrol help
with inflammation?
In humans, the evidence
of an anti-inflammatory effect
is sparse and conflicting.
About half of the studies show
a modest
anti-inflammatory effect,
but the other half
failed to find any.
The proof, however,
is in the pudding.
What about clinical effects
on inflammatory disease?
In rats and mice,
resveratrol can help
ameliorate the effects
of experimentally-induced
periodontitis,
the inflammatory gum disease.
However, it appears
to have no effect
on the progression
of chronic periodontitis
in human sufferers.
Resveratrol may help with
the inflammatory bowel disease
ulcerative colitis, though.
A pilot study
of 500 milligrams a day
of resveratrol for six weeks
resulted in significantly
decreased disease activity
and elevated quality of life
compared to placebo.
What about inflammatory
joint disease?
One pilot study
of 500 milligrams a day
of resveratrol
for knee osteoarthritis
found a decrease in pain
within a month,
but there was no control group;
so, the change can't
really be attributed
to starting the supplements.
However, a second pilot study,
a randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial,
found that the same dose
taken as an "add on"
to an anti-inflammatory drug
significantly improved
pain and function
within a month
in mild-to-moderate
knee osteoarthritis sufferers,
more than adding a placebo.
The one clinical trial
of rheumatoid arthritis
had a control group,
but no placebo,
though there were
objective signs of improvement
in disease activity after
taking 1000 milligrams a day
for three months.
Resveratrol may also be
beneficial
to combat menopausal symptoms.
Resveratrol has
some estrogenic activity.
Although it doesn't appear
to help with hormonal migraines,
it does appear to help
with a couple symptoms of PCOS,
polycystic ovary syndrome.
RESHAW—Resveratrol
for Healthy Ageing in Women—
is the longest study of effects
of resveratrol supplementation
in postmenopausal women.
Those randomized
to 75 milligrams
of resveratrol twice a day
suffered significantly fewer
physical menopausal symptoms,
including aches and pains,
and a general improvement
in overall well-being
compared to placebo.
The RESHAW study also looked
at bone loss prevention.
Unfortunately,
though animal studies
show protective effects
on bone tissue,
a meta-analysis
of human studies
on resveratrol supplementation
to improve bone quality
found no significant effect
on bone health markers
or bone mineral density
of the spine, hip,
or overall skeleton.
A similar story was found
for cognitive effects.
Most studies on resveratrol
for brain function
in animal models
show positive outcomes,
but meta-analyses
of human studies show
no significant effect
on memory,
processing speed,
executive function,
or global
cognitive performance,
which led reviewers to suggest
that resveratrol may be
a "cognitive enhancer
for mice only."
Most human cognition studies
found no effect
or mixed results—higher
performance on some tasks,
but lower performance on others,
compared to placebo,
resulting in
a "lack of interpretable
cognitive effects."
Some have suggested
the discrepancy
between the animal models
and the clinical data
is that the rodents
were massively dosed,
up to a gram per kilogram
of body weight a day,
which would be
like giving people
an entire bottle
of high-dose resveratrol
supplements at once.
Or, ironically,
it could be the opposite,
where the doses researchers
gave people were too large.
A dose-response study
found that human
cerebral blood flow
was maximally boosted
by the lowest dose
of resveratrol tested,
seventy-five milligrams a day.
So, when the RESHAW study
was developed,
that was the dose they used,
given twice a day.
RESHAW was primarily designed
to test the effects
of resveratrol
on cognitive performance.
Interim analyses at 14 weeks
and a year looked promising,
leading the researchers
to conclude that their findings
"support the adoption
of resveratrol
as a low-cost,
effective intervention
to help counteract the age-
and menopause-related
accelerated cognitive decline
in our ageing population."
However, by the end
of the two-year study,
it's not clear
if the apparent benefit
in overall cognition
survives adjustment
for multiple comparisons,
meaning there were so many
cognitive outcomes tested
that the few treatment
differences
may well have arisen
through chance.
What about cognitive benefit
for those who really need it?
Observational studies
find wine drinkers
tend to get less dementia,
but it's hard to disentangle
the social, cognitive,
and personality factors
that accompany
a wine drinking habit.
So, researchers decided
to put resveratrol to the test
for Alzheimer's disease.
A randomized double-blind,
placebo-controlled pilot
out of Cornell in 2006
kicked things off with a bang.
Patients with mild-to-moderate
Alzheimer's disease
who were randomized
to a 5 milligram
resveratrol concoction
twice a day
ended up with significantly
better cognition
after three months
compared to placebo.
There was a greater
than expected deterioration
in the placebo group, though,
suggesting that this may
have just been a fluke,
especially since an attempt
to replicate the study
with the same dose for a year
failed to find any effects
of statistical significance.
Maybe the researchers just
didn't use a high enough dose?
More than a hundred patients
with mild to moderate
Alzheimer's
were randomized to placebo
or an escalating dose
of resveratrol
starting at a hundred times
the dose
of the previous study—
500 milligrams once a day
and ending at a 1000 milligrams
twice a day.
After a year,
there were no significant
improvements in cognition
or the performance of activities
of daily living
compared to placebo.
Instead, there was
a significant acceleration
of brain volume loss.
At the end of the study,
there was triple
the brain volume loss
(3 percent versus 1 percent)
in the resveratrol group.
And the only other randomized,
double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial to date
found the same thing:
no significant
cognitive benefits
and the same tripling
of age-related brain shrinkage.
The authors tried to somehow
spin this as a positive,
like hey—maybe that's just
decreased brain swelling,
but as a team
of researchers wrote
in an understatement
of the year,
"It is difficult
to reconcile these effects
as potentially beneficial."